Guide to the Papers of Richard Phillips Feynman, 1933-1988
Archives
Richard Phillips Feynman papers,
1933-1988
Consult repository
Feynman, Richard Phillips, 1918-1988
39 linear feet
California Institute of Technology. Archives. Pasadena, California 91125
This collection documents the career of Nobel Prize winner Richard Phillips Feynman (1918-1988). It contains correspondence, biographical materials, course and lecture notes, speeches, manuscripts, publications, and technical notes relating to his work in quantum electrodynamics. Feynman served as Richard Chace Tolman Professor of Theoretical Physics at the California Institute of Technology from 1951 until his death.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research. Researchers must apply in writing for access.
Acquisition Information
The Papers were gifted to Caltech by Richard Feynman and Gweneth Feynman in two main installments, beginning in 1968.
The first group of papers, now boxes 1-20 of the collection, was donated by Feynman himself in 1968 and added to from time to time during his lifetime. It contains materials dating from circa 1933 to 1970. The second group, comprising just under three-fourths of the whole collection, occupies boxes 21-90. It was given to Caltech by Feynman's widow Gweneth early in 1989. Group 2 contains papers primarily from the 1970s and 1980s, although some older material is present. Supplements since 1994 occupy three boxes and have come from various donors outside the Feynman family.
Biography
Physicist Richard Feynman won his scientific renown through the development of quantum electrodynamics, or QED, a theory describing the interaction of particles and atoms in radiation fields. As a part of this work he invented what came to be known as "Feynman Diagrams," visual representations of space-time particle interactions. For this work he was awarded the Nobel Prize in physics, together with J. Schwinger and S. I. Tomonaga, in 1965. Later in his life Feynman became a prominent public figure through his association with the investigation of the space shuttle Challenger explosion and the publication of two best-selling books of personal recollections.
Feynman was born in the borough of Queens in New York City on May 11, 1918. He grew up and attended high school in Far Rockaway, New York. In 1939, he received his BS degree in physics from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He then attended Princeton University as a Proctor Fellow from 1940 to 1942, where he began his investigation of quantum electrodynamics under the supervision of J. A. Wheeler. He was awarded his PhD in 1942 for his thesis on the least action principle.
While still at Princeton, Feynman was recruited for the atomic bomb project. He was transferred to Los Alamos in 1942, where he headed a team undertaking complicated calculations using very primitive computers. While at Los Alamos, Feynman became good friends with Hans Bethe, who at the end of the war secured a position for Feynman as an associate professor of physics at Cornell. Feynman remained at Cornell from 1945 to 1951. During this time he formalized his theory of quantum electrodynamics and began to publish his results. He also participated in the Shelter Island Conference of 1947, which helped to determine the course of American physics in the atomic age. At this conference he introduced his theory of QED to the leading American physicists.
In 1951, Feynman accepted an offer to become the Richard Chace Tolman Professor of Theoretical Physics at the California Institute of Technology, a position he filled until his death. While at Caltech Feynman continued his work at the leading edge of theoretical physics, making important contributions to the study of liquid helium, particle physics, and later quantum chromodynamics. He also began his distinguished career as a teacher and lecturer. In 1961 and 1962 he delivered to Caltech's freshmen the introductory lectures that were later published as The Feynman Lectures on Physics.
In 1986, Feynman was asked to serve on the Presidential Commission investigating the space shuttle Challenger accident. In a dramatic fashion, Feynman publicly demonstrated the inelasticity of the shuttle's O-rings at near freezing temperatures, a leading cause of the disaster. He also contributed an extended appendix to the Committee's report, highlighting the technical and administrative deficiencies of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's space program.
Feynman's many interests outside of science, such as his fondness for codes and safecracking, his bongo drums, his theatrical appearances, his artwork, plus his experiments in out-of-body experiences, are well documented in his autobiographies, as well as in his papers at Caltech.
Feynman continued his scientific work and his lecturing activities up until his death on February 15, 1988, after a long battle with a rare form of cancer.
Scope and Content of Collection
The working papers, correspondence, manuscripts and related materials of Richard Phillips Feynman (1918-1988) form the collection known as the Feynman Papers in the California Institute of Technology Archives. Feynman was the Richard Chace Tolman Professor of Theoretical Physics at Caltech from 1951 to 1988.
The Papers were gifted to Caltech by Richard Feynman and Gweneth Feynman in two main installments, beginning in 1968. Caltech has title to the Papers themselves, while the Feynman heirs retain literary and publication rights. The Feynman Lectures on Physics and the Lectures on Gravitation form an exception, in that Caltech is the copyright holder in these publications.
The first group of papers, now boxes 1-20 of the collection, was donated by Feynman himself in 1968 and added to from time to time during his lifetime. It contains materials dating from circa 1933 to 1970. The second group, comprising just under three-fourths of the whole collection, occupies boxes 21-90. It was given to Caltech by Feynman's widow Gweneth early in 1989. Group 2 contains papers primarily from the 1970s and 1980s, although some older material is present.
The two groups of papers have been kept separate, although box numbering is continuous throughout the collection. The guide to the collection is in two parts, and researchers must expect to consult both parts. At the time the second group of papers was processed, an effort was made to create an arrangement parallel to that of group 1. However, the different content and larger scope of group 2 eventually resulted in a somewhat different scheme.
Correspondence:
The Feynman collection contains a large amount of both incoming and outgoing correspondence. Feynman's scientific contacts include many of the greatest names in twentieth-century physics: Hans Bethe, Niels Bohr, Enrico Fermi, Stephen Hawking, Werner Heisenberg, J. Robert Oppenheimer, Hideki Yukawa--to name only a few. In Group 1, correspondence has been spread over four sections: correspondence (largely with individual colleagues), miscellaneous or general correspondence, publication correspondence, and, in the biographical section, a small number of personal letters.
For Group 2, an attempt was made to pull both personal, general, and publication correspondence into one main section, Section I. However, when letters demonstrated both intellectual and physical links with other documents, their original contextual relationships were maintained. Thus, publication correspondence will be found both in Section I and in Section VI. Fan mail surrounding Feynman's television appearances, his two autobiographies, and his Nobel Prize has been placed in Section II, Biographical, as has other correspondence relating to his business and consulting activities documented there.
Course and Lecture Notes:
Feynman's lecture courses at institutions in Southern California other than Caltech, and even outside the U.S., are represented in Group 2. Of special interest are the courses Feynman gave, in addition to those he attended, at Hughes Aircraft Company, and the sets of lectures that were later published as Statistical Mechanics and QED (originally the Mautner Lectures, which were in turn predated by the Robb Lectures, first delivered at the University of Aukland, New Zealand). Material pertaining to the publication of these lecture series is found in Group 2 correspondence under the respective publishers.
Talks, Speeches, Conferences:
In this category are those lectures delivered for a special occasion or purpose, usually as single lectures, but sometimes as a series, and in both formal and informal settings. This category overlaps somewhat with Course Notes and Lectures. In Group 1, these materials are to be found under Professional Organizations and Meetings (Section III) and Manuscripts (Section V). In Group 2, they are arranged under Section V in chronological order, when dated, and in a subsection of undated talks. Folders in this category contain a wide variety of talk-related documents, from holograph notes to correspondence to slides, figures, or transparencies.
Publications:
Group 1 contains a small section of publication correspondence (Group 1, Section IV), mostly pertaining to Feynman's book or monograph publishers; in Group 2, similar correspondence has been placed in the main correspondence section (Group 2, Section I). Group 2's Section VI lists Feynman's publications by title in chronological order. Folders contain a variety of material, from holograph notes to correspondence to proofs and prints. Researchers should note that formal reprints have been grouped at the end of Group 2, in Section IX.
Working Notes and Calculations:
The vast majority of Feynman's working notes are located in Group 2. A representative sample from his early years appears in Group 1, Section V. Of special interest in this group are notebooks from his student days, beginning ca 1933. The notes in Group 2 capture the breadth and depth of Feynman's thought, as well as reflecting many aspects of his personality. They cover a wide range of subjects, from quantum electrodynamics and later quantum chromodynamics to biology and computers. The notes also reflect Feynman's working style. They are sometimes carefully organized into notebooks that were rigorously dated, such as the binders dated between 1966 and 1987 at the beginning of Group 2, Section VII. Unfortunately for researchers, these are the exception. The great mass of Feynman's working notes are scattered on miscellaneous sheets of papers, envelopes, placemats, and seemingly whatever else was at hand when thoughts struck him. Feynman occasionally took time to organize these into a system for files, although only a small fraction of his notes found their way into such a system. The great majority was left in a scattered condition and grouped during the processing of the papers as well as possible by subject matter. Many miscellaneous papers remain.
Work of Others:
Feynman officially maintained neutrality on the work of his contemporaries, but informal commentaries in the form of notes and marginal glosses on the work of others abound in his papers. A small segment of such materials can be found in Group 1, Section V. A large amount of work by others, both with and without Feynman's commentary, forms Group 2's Section VIII. A preponderance of material on computers dictated an arrangement in which computer-related projects are categorized separately. Individuals whose work is strongly represented--largely Caltech colleagues, students, or collaborators--are listed singly; otherwise materials have been listed by subject.
Note on use of Guide:
In writing the guide to the collection, the archivists have observed certain conventions, particularly in the area of manuscript description. Square brackets ([]) are used to mark editorial insertions, such as titles created by the archivist which are not derived directly from the manuscripts themselves. Brackets are also used to signify unnumbered pages in a manuscript.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection.
Physicists
Bethe, Hans Albrecht, 1906-; Bohr, Niels Henrik David, 1885-1962; Fermi, Enrico, 1901-1954; Hawking, Stephen W., 1942-; Heisenberg, Werner, 1901-1976; Oppenheimer, J. Robert, 1904-1967
Subjects
Computers; Gravitation--Research; Particles (Nuclear physics); Physics--Study and teaching; Quantum chromodynamics; Quantum electrodynamics; Quantum theory; Space shuttles--Accidents--Investigation--United States; Challenger (Space shuttle)
Corporations
California Institute of Technology
Genres and Forms of Materials
Calculations; Lecture notes; Manuscripts; Notebooks; Technical notes
Related Collections
Researchers should also consult the Caltech Archives' Historical Files, which contain much miscellaneous material on Richard Feynman acquired from many sources. Similarly the Photo Archives offer a selection of images, obtained in a similar way. The Audio and Video Collections contain substantial Feynman material; researchers should consult the specific index.
Manuscript collections at Caltech which contain materials of particular relevance to Feynman include the Papers of Robert Leighton and the Caltech course lecture notes by Bruce H. Morgan.
Container List
- Group I
  - Section I: Correspondence
    - American Philosophical Society 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anderson, Herbert L. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ashkin, Julius 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Australian National University (E. W. Titterton, M. L. Oliphant) 1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - A Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bacher, Robert F. 1949-1950; 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Beadle, George W., M.D.; 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Bethe, Hans A. 1946, 1948, 1951, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Birge, Raymond T. 1945, 1947, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bohm, David 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bohr, Niels 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Breuckner, Keith 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bronk, Detlev 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Brown, Laurie M. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bush, Vannevar 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Butler, Stuart (Blatt, J. M.; Schafroth, M. R., 1955); 1960, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - B Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Chandrasekhar, Subrahmanyan 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Chicago, University of, Lecture 1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Christy, Robert F. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Cohen, Arthur M. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Condon, Ed 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Corben, Bert and Malaika 1947-1964 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Creutz, Edward 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Critchfield, Charles L. 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - C Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Dresden, Max 1960 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - DuBridge, Lee A. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - DuMond, Jesse 1961, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Dyson, Freeman 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - D Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Einstein Film 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Employment Offers 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - E Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Fermi, Enrico 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Fernández-Moran, Humberto 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - F Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Gell-Mann, Murray 1959 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - General Electric 1946 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Goudsmit, Sam A. 1949, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Guth, Eugene 1960 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - G Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Heisenberg, Werner 1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hessaby, Mahmoud 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hirshberg, Richard 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Hoffman, Banesh 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - H Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - I Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Jehle, Herbert 1959; N.D.; 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Judd, David L. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - J Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Keller, Joseph 1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Kerner, Ed 1949 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - K Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Lattes, Cesar 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Lévy, Maurice 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Lomanitz, Ross 1960, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Luria, Salvador 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - L Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Mano, Koichi 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Marshak, Robert E. 1957, 1960, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Marshall, Leona 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Andre Maurois Visit 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Mercereau, James E. 1952, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Metropolis, Nicholas 1949, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Miniature Electric Motor 1960-1961, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - MIT Centennial "The Future of Physics" 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Morette, Cecile 1950 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - M Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - National Academy of Science 1959-1961, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Neddermeyer, Seth H. 1949 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - N Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Oppenheimer, J. Robert 1946-1947, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - O Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Panofsky, Wolfgang 1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Perez-Mendez, Victor 1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Piccioni, Oreste 1960 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Prigogine, Ilya 1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - P Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Richtmyer, Robert D. 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Rojansky, Vladimir 1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - R Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Sandage, Allan 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Scalettar, Richard 1960 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Schiff, Leonard I. 1951, 1960-1961, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Segal, Irving 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Segré, Emilio 1961 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Seitz, Frederick 1946 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Smith, Lloyd P. 1947, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Smyth, H. D. 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Stahl, Franklin W. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Sutherland, Sir Gordon 1960 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Synge, John L. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - S Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - T Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ulam, Stan M. 1960, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - U Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Von Neumann, John 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - V Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Weinberg, Joseph 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Weiner, Norbert 1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Weisskopf, Victor 1948, 1961-1962, 1964, 1966, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Welton, Theodore A. 1948-1950, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Wheeler, John A. (including notes on Feynman's thesis) 1942, 1945, 1949, 1951, 1961, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Wigner, Eugene P. 1946, 1949, 1955, 1965, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Wilson, Thomas J. 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - W Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Y Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Zacharias, Jerrold R. 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Z Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified and Miscellaneous Items (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Section II: Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Army Scientific Advisory Panel 1954 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Program About "Time" 1957-1962 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Recommendations - People, Proposals (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "New Math" Letters I 1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "New Math" Letters II 1965-1968 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Students' Letters 1961-1970 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Acceptances 1948-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Declinations 1949-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 1967, A - L (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 1967, M - W (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 1970, A - M (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 1970, N - W (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Section III: Professional Organizations And Meetings
    - Conferences
      - International Colloquium on "Fundamental Particles and Nuclei" 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Moscow Conference on Quantum Electrodynamics 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Relativity and Gravitation, Warsaw, Poland 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Galileo Conference, Italy 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Reports
      - Atomic Energy Commission, "The Calculation of Critical Masses Including the Effects of the Distribution of Neutron Energies" 1947 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Rochester Conference Notes ca 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Evaluation of "A Rational Method of Forecasting Natural Gas Production and Discoveries" 1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Cornell Meeting on the Nature of Time 1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Proceedings, Conference on High Energy Two Body Reactions 1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Section IV: Publication Correspondence
    - W. A. Benjamin, Inc. 1961-1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - McGraw-Hill 1955-1966 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder Folders 12-13)
  - Section V: Manuscripts
    - Talks
      - "The Reaction of the Absorber as the Mechanism of Radioactive Damping" 1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "The Concept of Probability in Quantum Mechanics" 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - John Danz Lectures: 1963, University of Washington (correspondence and transcripts) (Box 6, Folder 2.1)
    - Notes on Manuscripts
      - Josephson Junction (Mercereau's work) (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - "Action at a Distance in Quantum Theory" by John Wheeler (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - "On Field Theories with Non-Localized Interaction" by Claude Bloch (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - "Radioactive Corrections to p-e Decay" by Sam M. Berman (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - "Variational Determination of Atomic Wave Functions" by P. Morse and L. Young (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Notes by Other Scientists
      - Properties of Pi Mesons, Hans A. Bethe 1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Pion Photoproduction Formulas, R. L. Walker 1965 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Papers
      - "Closed Loop and Tree Diagrams" March 1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - "The Present State of Quantum Electrodynamics" Solvay Conference 1961 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Abstract, "The Quantum Theory of Gravitation" 1964 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - 5 Slides and Paper T5 Theory of Positrons (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - "Atom Theory of Liquid Helium" July 21, 1953 (Abstract of a paper to be presented at the Theoretical Physics Conference in Tokyo, September 1953. Notas de Fisica No. 12, 1953. Centro Brasiliero de Pesquisas Fisicas) (Box 6, Folder 13.1)
    - Notes for Other Lectures
      - "Theory and Application of Mercereau's Super- conducting Circuits" October 29, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - "Current Algebras and Strong Interactions," Transcript 1966 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - "Time in Physics and Evolutionary History" 1968 at Berkeley (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Notes for Public Lectures (includes "Inertia") (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Manuscript ["Physics and the Constituents of Matter"] (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Manuscript, "Quantum Theory of Least Action" (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Abstract, "The Qualitative Behavior of Yang-Mills Theory in 2+1 Dimensions" 1981 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Lecture Notes for Courses
      - Untitled "405" 1946 (at Cornell University) (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Quantum Mechanics 1947 (at Cornell University) Fall (folder 2); 2nd term (folder 3) (Box 7, Folder Folders 2-3)
      - Advanced Quantum Mechanics (at Cornell) (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - High Energy Nuclear and Meson Phenomena 1951 (Brazil) (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder Folders 5-6)
      - .6.1 Misc. Lecture Notes, Brazil, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - High Energy Phenomena and Meson Theories 1951 (at CIT) (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Quantum Mechanics (at CIT) (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Quantum Electrodynamics 1953 (at CIT) (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Quantum Electrodynamics and Meson Theories 1950 (at CIT) (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Theoretical Nuclear Physics (at CIT) (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Theory of High Energy Phenomena 1951 and Meson Theory Notes (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Electrodynamics (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Energy Flux; The Behavior of Waves (Box 8, Folder 4)